<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Privacy on AstonishingElixirs</title>
    <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/tags/privacy/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Privacy on AstonishingElixirs</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>ck_howard@yahoo.com (Chris Howard)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>ck_howard@yahoo.com (Chris Howard)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ckhoward.github.io/tags/privacy/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Deploying a Tor Hidden Service with DigitalOcean</title>
      <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/post/tor-hidden-service/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>ck_howard@yahoo.com (Chris Howard)</author>
      <guid>https://ckhoward.github.io/post/tor-hidden-service/</guid>
      <description>Deploying a Tor Hidden Service with DigitalOcean A quick primer on Tor hidden services The Tor protocol picks 3 onion routers at random, builds circuits to them, treating them as introduction (or contact) points; since this is a circuit, there is no direct connection, so no IP addresses are shared, just public keys. These public keys work toward &amp;ldquo;shaking hands&amp;rdquo; at a rendezvous point. If the handshake happens, the rendezvous point connects Alice&amp;rsquo;s and Bob&amp;rsquo;s circuits, and then they can communicate anonymously.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>FIXBUX: A Web-extension to Safeguard Users from Themselves [Javascript]</title>
      <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/post/fixbux/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 12 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>ck_howard@yahoo.com (Chris Howard)</author>
      <guid>https://ckhoward.github.io/post/fixbux/</guid>
      <description>Overview It would seem that people are becoming more conscious of behavior&amp;rsquo;s role in retaining, taking back, and even losing privacy. Privacy technology isn&amp;rsquo;t currently a solution to privacy issues, so it is becoming more important to consider how we interact with these technologies, and how we make decisions. We have a greater propensity to share when our friends share, when we trust the technology maintainers, and defaults surprisingly dictate the way we behave, so what happens when you opt-in, by default, to share your social network data with a host of third parties?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>