<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Fixed on Chris Howard</title>
    <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/fixed/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Fixed on Chris Howard</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-US</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 16:52:01 -0700</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://ckhoward.github.io/fixed/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>projects</title>
      <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/projects/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 16:52:01 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ckhoward.github.io/projects/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;blog/terrorist-targets-exploratory/&#34;&gt;Terrorist Targets&lt;/a&gt; is a brief exploratory analysis on the targets of some elected terrorist organizations. The dataset was taken from The Global Terrorism Database. A histogram was created to look at which entities were the most popular targets that terrorists choose to attack. From there, mosaic plots are made to show the differences in terrorist organizations, not only in who they attack, but also in how they carry out that attack. This is the one project that code will not be posted for, in the name of academic integrity.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>about</title>
      <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/about/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2017 16:46:22 -0700</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://ckhoward.github.io/about/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Hi. I live in Tucson, Arizona, and I do data analysis.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I created this site as a means to learn. I find it to be a useful way to articulate my thoughts, and I&amp;rsquo;ve learned that the social element helps with retention. If I talk to somebody about something I just read, it becomes more ingrained in memory. While blogging can be audienceless and is written rather than spoken, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to acheive the same social effect.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Additionally, I will use the projects page to hold myself accountable for starting &lt;em&gt;and finishing&lt;/em&gt; more projects. Maybe somebody will see something they like. Maybe I will get constructive criticism. Regardless, I&amp;rsquo;m hoping to inspire readers at least a little bit, and improve my communication skills in the process.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I like to write about politics, mind, terrorism, cyber-security, disinformation, and culture.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Types of Analyses:&lt;/strong&gt; statistical, geospatial, linguistic, and network&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Tools:&lt;/strong&gt; Python, R, JavaScript (d3.js), ArcGIS&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Wanna get in touch?&lt;/strong&gt; Send me a message at christopherh@email.arizona.edu&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>