<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>R on AstonishingElixirs</title>
    <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/tags/r/</link>
    <description>Recent content in R on AstonishingElixirs</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <managingEditor>ck_howard@yahoo.com (Chris Howard)</managingEditor>
    <webMaster>ck_howard@yahoo.com (Chris Howard)</webMaster>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://ckhoward.github.io/tags/r/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>An Introduction to the Stylo Library [R]</title>
      <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/post/a-guide-to-stylo/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 27 Dec 2017 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      <author>ck_howard@yahoo.com (Chris Howard)</author>
      <guid>https://ckhoward.github.io/post/a-guide-to-stylo/</guid>
      <description>An Introduction to the Stylo Library What is Stylometry? Stylometry uses linguistic style to determine who authored some anonymous piece of writing, and it has diverse applications. The authorship of some suicide notes may be questionable. Most forum users have aliases in an attempt to anonymize themselves. And some authors publish their writings under pseudonyms. In these varying cases, stylometry can be used to deanonymize an author.
What is Stylo?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Sentiment Analysis of First GOP Debate in 2015 [R]</title>
      <link>https://ckhoward.github.io/post/gop-debate-sentiment-analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 17 Jun 2017 14:50:42 -0700</pubDate>
      <author>ck_howard@yahoo.com (Chris Howard)</author>
      <guid>https://ckhoward.github.io/post/gop-debate-sentiment-analysis/</guid>
      <description>A Statistical Analysis of Sentiments Every four years, the United States goes through the process of electing (or re-electing) its president. Politics becomes a popular topic of conversation, and inadvertently, a popular emotional outlet. Our digital landscape has — mostly textually, but sometimes by video or podcast — granted the ability for people to express their thoughts and feelings on political ideas and events, en masse. Suffice to say, an examination of people&amp;rsquo;s language in these expressions can yield many useful insights into human (or American) character and the influence of rhetoric on political philosophy and national pride.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>